现在，我们将讨论关于干扰的联合控制。而最明显的干扰，
Now, we are going to talk about joint control with disturbances. And the most obvious disturbance,
机器人手臂上最常见的干扰是重力引起的干扰。想像
the most common disturbance on a robotic arm is the disturbance due to gravity. Imagine
这种特殊配置的PUMA机器人操纵器。它的手臂伸展了
a PUMA robot manipulator in this particular configuration. It’s got its arm stretched
横向水平，你能想象手臂的重量很大。所以，有一个很大的
out horizontally and can you imagine that arm weighs quite a lot. So, there is a large
肩关节扭矩，肘关节也有很大的扭矩
torque on the shoulder joint and there’s also a large torque on the elbow joint that
是必需的，以保持手臂处于水平姿势。
are required in order to keep the arm in that horizontal pose.
我们可以看一下该特定场景的更简化版本。考虑一下我们
We can look at a more simplified version of that particular scenario. Consider here we
有一个连接到水平杆的电动机。酒吧设有一个中心
have an electric motor which is connected to a horizontal bar. The bar has a centre
质量和质心是距电动机轴的距离r。和酒吧
of mass and the centre of mass is a distance r from the axis of the motor. And the bar
有一个m的质量和杆有一个重力，这是由于重力作用力
has got a mass of m and the bar has a weight force, that’s the force due to gravity acting
在质心上，这是mg向下作用的力。
on the centre of mass and that is a force of mg acting in the downward direction.
现在，具有杠杆臂长度r的mg力导致作用在电动机上的扭矩
Now, a force of mg with a lever arm length of r results in a torque acting on the motor
轴和扭矩的大小由质量乘以重力给出
shaft and the magnitude of that torque is given by the mass times the gravitational
加速度乘以质心距电机轴的距离。在这
acceleration times the distance of the centre of mass from the axis of the motor. In this
在特定情况下，扭矩以逆时针方向作用。中心
particular case, the torque is acting in a counter clockwise direction. The centre of
质量想要垂直向下移动。如果我们真的为我们看的情况做数学计算
mass wants to move vertically downward. If we actually do the maths for the case we looked
刚才，PUMA机器人用它的手臂处于水平配置，扭矩大小
at a moment ago, the PUMA robot with its arm in a horizontal configuration, the torque
在肩关节是14牛顿米。如果我认为我的手臂长一米，
on the shoulder joint is 14 Newton meters. If I assume that my arm is one meter long,
这相当于我的手臂伸出四公斤;那太漂亮了
that’s equivalent to holding four kilograms with my arm outstretched; that’s a pretty
虽然在肩关节上有很多扭矩，但是很难做到
difficult thing to do, though there’s a lot of torque acting on the shoulder joint
PUMA机器人。显然，这将对肩部的控制产生影响
of the PUMA robot. And clearly, this is going to have an effect on the control of the shoulder
联合。那么，现在让我们来看看我们的机器人关节控制器的更多细节。这是
joint. So, let’s look now in some more detail at our robot joint controller. And this is
我们在上一课中介绍的方框图。这是一个反馈控制器。该
a block diagram we introduced in the last lecture. It’s a feedback controller. The
机器人关节控制器的输入是所需的位置，θ星。和输出
input to the robot joint controller is the desired position, theta star. And the output
联合控制器的实际关节位置是由θ表示的。正如我们讨论的那样
of the joint controller is the actual joint position denoted by theta. And as we discussed
在上一节课中，我正在使用许多这些变量的拉普拉斯变换;所以没有
in the last lecture, I’m using the Laplace transform of many of these variables; so not
他们在时域中的反应，但他们在拉普拉斯域的反应。我表示
their response in the time domain but their response in the Laplace domain. And I denote
拉普拉斯域使用大写字母。所以，这就是我使用资本theta的原因
the Laplace domain by using capital letters. So, that’s why I’ve used capital theta
在这里和这里。现在在这个控制循环中，我们有一个控制律，它可能是一个比例
here and here. Now within this control loop, we have a control law, it might be a proportional
衍生控制器，它可能是一个比例积分微分控制器，称为a
derivative controller, it might be a proportional integral derivative controller known as a
PID控制器，我们有电机驱动器的增益，我们有传感器的增益
PID controller and we have the gain of the motor driver and we have the gain of the sensor
我们有执行器的传递功能，即驱动的电动机
and we have the transfer function of the actuator, that’s the electric motor which is driving
关节。并且它具有诸如电动机转矩常数KM之类的参数;惯性，
the joint. And that has parameters such as the motor torque constant, KM; the inertia,
焦耳;和粘性摩擦，B;而S当然是拉普拉斯算子。现在这是一个
J; and the viscous friction, B; and S is of course the Laplace operator. Now this is a
非常理想化的表现。不存在诸如重力所表示的干扰
very idealistic representation. There is no disturbance such as the force of gravity represented
在这个框图中。那么，让我们为此做些什么。
in this block diagram. So, let’s do something about that.
我所做的就是将电机转矩从执行器转换中移出
What I’ve done is I’ve moved the motor torque constant out of the actuator transfer
功能，并使其成为一个明确的增益块，你可以在这里看到。那个的输出
function and made it an explicit gain block which you can see here. The output of that
增益阻塞是实际的电机转矩。现在我所做的实际上是分开的
gain block is the actual motor torque. Now what I’ve done is actually separated
电机分为两个部分。我有一个产生扭矩的组件，我有另一个
the motor into two components. I have a component which generates a torque and I have another
代表电动机惯性和粘性摩擦的部件。
component which represents the inertia and viscous friction of the motor.
现在，我将介绍另一个求和点，这是我们注入干扰的地方
Now, I’m going to introduce another summing junction which is a where we inject the disturbance
扭矩。因此，在这个特定的求和点处，我们得到了电机的转矩之和
torque. So at this particular summing junction, we have the sum of the torque which the motor
创造并增加了来自干扰源的扭矩。它
creates and I add to that the torque which is coming from the disturbance source. It
可能是由于引力。这可能是由于我们谈到的像库仑摩擦之类的东西
might be due to gravity. It might be due to something like Coulomb friction which we talked
在上一讲中，TD是该干扰扭矩的拉普拉斯变换。
about in the last lecture and TD is the Laplace transform of that disturbance torque.
引入干扰，即使是持续干扰，也会引起误差
The introduction of a disturbance, even a constant disturbance, will cause an error
在里面。如果我们现在看一下简化原理图的增益，我们就得到了实际的角度
in the. If we now look a gain at that simplified schematic, we have the actual angle of the
机器人链接，我们有机器人链接所需的角度。我们可以看到实际的
robot link and we have the desired angle of the robot link. And we can see that the actual
角度有点不同，它是向下的，因为重力拉动它
angle is a little bit different, it’s downwards because the force of gravity is pulling it
向下并且马达控制器没有完全反对那个重力。控制器
downwards and the motor controller hasn’t fully opposed that force of gravity. The controller
我们刚刚使用的是比例加微分控制器，通常称为PD控制器
that we just used is a proportional-plus-derivative controller often known as a PD controller
它在机器人系统中非常常用。因此PD产生的扭矩
and it’s very very commonly used in robotic systems. So the torque produced by the PD
控制器是增益P乘以我想要关节角度之间的误差，
controller is a gain P multiplied by the error between where I want the joint angle to be,
theta星，实际的关节角度θ加上另一个增益称为D乘以
theta star, and the actual joint angle theta plus another gain termed D multiplied by the
θ点的关节速度。如果我们考虑稳态的情况
velocity of the joint that’s theta dot. If we consider the steady state case where
关节没有移动，它被重力向下偏转;但它没有动
the joint is not moving, it’s deflected downwards by gravity; but it’s not moving
任何进一步向下;它处于平衡状态;那么theta点将等于零。所以，
any further downwards; it’s in equilibrium; then theta dot will be equal to zero. So,
我们可以消除那个词。如果关节处于平衡状态，则产生扭矩
we can eliminate that term. And if the joint is in equilibrium, then the torque generated
通过电动机及其控制器必须等于重力引起的扭矩。所以，我们可以写
by the motor and its controller must be equal to the torque due to gravity. So, we can write
这种关系。如果我们做一些重新排列，我们可以看到错误
this relationship. And if we do a little bit of rearrangement, we can see that the error
在我们想要关节的位置和关节实际位置之间，等于MGR
between where we want the joint to be and where the joint actually is, is equal to MGR
除以P，我们的比例增益。现在，有一些非常有趣的后果
divided by P, our proportional gain. Now, there are some very interesting consequences
那个。一个是如果我们想要减少这个错误，我们需要增加价值
of that. And one is it if we want to reduce this error, we need to increase the value
P.如果P更大，因为它在分母中，那么它会产生很大的误差
of P. If P is bigger because it’s in the denominator, then it makes the error much
小多了。我们将重新审视机器人关节模型
much smaller. We are going to revisit the robot joint model
我们在上一课中在Simulink中构建的。我们已经把一些参数的值
that we built in Simulink in the last lecture. We’ve put the values of some of the parameters
进入工作区，这是我们的模型，我们将带来有用的调色板
into the workspace and this is our model and we’re going to bring in my palette of useful
Simulink对象也是如此。我要做的第一件事就是移动所有这些东西
Simulink objects as well. The first thing I’m going to do is to move all of this stuff
在这里，我将介绍一个新的增益块，我将要介入
across here and I’m going to introduce a new gain block which I’m going to drop in
这里。而我要做的是从分子中删除称为KM的增益
here. And what I’m going to do is to remove the gain termed KM from the numerator of the
传递函数，我将把它放在这个块中。所以功能上，这个
transfer function and I’m going to put it into this block here. So functionally, this
是完全一样的。我们有一个增益KM乘以这个传递函数。的输出
is exactly the same. We have a gain KM multiplying this transfer function here. The output of
该增益块是施加到电动机电枢的转矩。
this gain block is the torque that’s applied to the armature of the electric motor.
现在我要做的是引入扰动力矩。要做到这一点，我需要
Now what I’m going to do is to introduce a disturbance torque. To do that, I need to
找到一个求和点，并且有一个求和点，我将编辑这个
find a summing junction and there’s a summing junction and I’m going to edit this so that
在向上的方向上有一个加分。我认为这样就可以了，我要去了
it has got a plus in the upward direction. I think that will do the trick and I’m going
要移除那根电线，将求和点放在这里，从那里画一根电线到那里。
to remove that wire, put the summing junction in here, draw a wire from there to there.
干扰力将来自阶梯函数，这就是源。
And the disturbance force is going to come from a step function, that’s the source.
开始了。我希望我的步骤在模拟中的第5时间发生。模拟
Here we go. And I want my step to occur at time five in the simulation. The simulation
运行10秒钟，因此干扰将在5秒钟发生。因此，它有一个
runs for 10 seconds, so the disturbance will occur at five seconds. Hence, it has got a
价值一。所以，我将把它连接到求和中
value of one. So, I’m going to connect that into the summing
结。好吧，我们现在所拥有的是一个像以前一样的模型。但现在，
junction. All right, so what we have now is a model like what we had before. But now,
我可以引入干扰扭矩，该扭矩也作用在电枢的电枢上
I can introduce a disturbance torque which also acts on the armature of the electric
发动机。现在有两个扭矩作用在电枢上。有产生的扭矩
motor. There are now two torques acting on the armature. There is the torque generated by
控制器和外部干扰有扭矩。现在让我们跑吧
the controller and there is the torque by this external disturbance. Now let’s run
那。我将把范围纳入视野，所以我们可以看到，只是一点点，
that. I’ll bring the scope into view, so we can see that, just across a little bit,
并运行我的模拟。结果看起来像这样。让我们放大一点，让我们
and run my simulation. And the result looks like this. Let’s zoom in a little bit, let's
自动调整，我们可以看到电机一直跟随方波移动
auto-scale that and we can see that the motor has been following the square wave moving
介于减1和加1之间。但是当应用外部干扰时，我们就会看到
between minus one and plus one. But when the external disturbance is applied, we see that
这对电机的位置产生了很大的影响。我们可以看到它
that has got a really big influence on the position of the motor. We could see that it
已经向上移动，现在正在3-1/2和5-1/2之间移动。很明显这是外在的
has moved up and is now moving between the 3-1/2 and 5-1/2. So clearly this external
力对电机控制器的性能产生了很大的影响，而且还没有
force has had a really big impact on the performance of the motor controller and it’s not doing
我们希望它做的工作。所以，我们已经看到有一些后果
the job that we want it to do. So, we’ve seen that there are some consequences
增加比例增益P.我们可以使用的另一种策略是添加积分
of increasing the proportional gain P. Another strategy that we can use is to add an integral
术语和将我们的控制器变成比例积分和微分控制器
term and that turns our controller into a proportional integral and derivative controller
通常称为PID控制器，我们在这里添加的是积分项。
very commonly known as a PID controller and what we’ve added here is the integral term.
我们有另一个增益I，即积分增益，它乘以时间积分
We have another gain I which is the integral gain and that multiplies the time integral
位置误差，θ星减去theta。从直觉的角度来看，这意味着是否存在
of the position error, theta star minus theta. What this means, in intuitive terms, is if there
是一个位置误差，积分随着时间的推移逐渐增加，增加了
is a position error, the integral gradually increases over time and that increases the
施加在关节上的扭矩，以抵消该特定误差。
torque that’s applied to the joint so as to counter that particular error.
现在我们要做的是增加系统的比例增益并看看
Now what we are going to do is to increase the proportional gain of the system and see
如果我们可以改进，那么这里是控制器的参数。比例
if we can improve things, so here are the parameters of our controller. The proportional
增益等于一。我要加倍。我要把它等于两个。
gain is equal to one. I’m going to double that. I’m going to make it equal to two.
关闭它，我们将再次运行我们的模拟，看看步骤响应会发生什么。
Close that and we’ll run our simulation again and see what happens to the step response.
现在我们看到干扰的影响已经减弱。我们现在可以看到了
And now we see that the effect of the disturbance has been attenuated. We can see now that the
干扰的影响较小，因为我们增加了比例增益。
effect of the disturbance is less because we’ve increased the proportional gain.
让我们再增加一些。我要把它增加到4，运行它
Let’s increase it some more. I’m going to increase it to a value of four, run that
再次模拟。现在我们看到扰动的影响甚至进一步减少了
simulation again. Now we see that the effect of disturbance is even further reduced, but
我们也注意到我们的方波响应的射击量很大，
we’ve also noticed that the amount over shoot on our square wave response is much,
更高，这是增加比例增益的结果，我们可以绕过
much higher and this is a consequence of increasing the proportional gain and we can get around
在某种程度上，通过增加衍生术语的数量，增加数量
that to some extent by increasing the amount of derivative term, increase the amount of
阻尼会减少过冲量。但除此之外还有其他后果。
damping that will reduce the amount of overshoot. But there are other consequences besides.
我要做的是在此图表中添加另一个范围。并在此引入范围
What I am going to do is to add another scope to this diagram. And bring in the scope here
它将要做的是显示电机产生的扭矩
and what it’s going to do is to show the torque that’s generated by the motor and
让我们运行这个。所以，我有一个新的范围，让我们打开它
let’s run this. So, I have a new scope, let's open that up
我们在这里看到的是我们要求电机产生的扭矩。现在，我们可以
and what we see here is the torque that we're asking the motor to generate. Now, we can
看到大约加五到五牛顿米之间的扭矩有尖峰
see that there is spikes in the torque between about plus five to minus five newton meters
要求电动机产生的扭矩。随着我们增加比例增益，
of torque for asking the motor to produce. As we increase the proportional gain, the
我们要求电机生产的最大扭矩将不断增加。
maximum torque that we ask the motor to produce will keep increasing.
任何真正的电动机都具有有限的扭矩能力。它不能产生无限大的扭矩。
Any real motor has got a finite torque capability. It can't produce an infinite amount of torque.
现在，最终，这就是增加比例增益的策略
Now, ultimately, this is where the strategy of increasing the proportional gain will come
粘住。因此，增加比例增益，我们要求电机提供更大的扭矩
unstuck. So, increase the proportional gain we’re asking the motor provide more torque
最终，我们要求它产生比实际更大的扭矩。
and eventually, we’re be asking it to produce more torque than it actually can do.
所以，我们已经看到了增加比例增益的效果。我们已经看到了这种效果
So, we’ve seen the effects of increasing the proportional gain. We’ve seen the effect
添加一个整数项。所以，第三种策略，通常用来消除这种
of adding an integral term. So, third strategy, that’s often use to eliminate this kind
错误，这是介绍所谓的前馈术语。
of error and that’s to introduce what’s called a feed forward term.
这是我们之前的框图，我们将介绍前馈控制
Here's our block diagram from earlier and we are going to introduce a feed forward control
术语。前馈控制的关键部分是，在很多情况下，我们实际上可以计算
term. And the key part of feed forward control, is that in many cases, we actually can compute
干扰力将是什么。因此，在重力的情况下，如果我们知道关节
what the disturbance force will be. So, in the case of gravity, if we know the joint
角度，我们可以计算每个关节的重力。
angles, we can compute what the gravity force is on each of the joints.
因此，我们可以估算出重力干扰是什么，并得到了它
So, we can come up with an estimate of what the gravity disturbance is and this is got
对我们真的很有帮助。这是我们应该对干扰的额外了解
to be really helpful to us. This is extra knowledge about the disturbance in we should
能够用它来消除干扰。我们这样做的方式是我们添加另一个
be able to use it to cancel the disturbance out. The way we do that is we add another
总结我们的控制法的结合，它有一个负面的迹象，所以，这
summing junction into our control law and it's got a negative sign on it and so, this
有一个负增益或它是一个减法。然后使其完成所有工作，平衡
has got a negative gain or it's a subtraction. And then to make it to all work, to balance
我们必须在这里增加收益。这是KdKm的一个收益。
out, we have to add a gain in here. This is a gain of one on KdKm.
如果你考虑一下，如果我们在这里得到估计的扭矩，我们在这里除以KD和KM。
If you think about it, if we have our estimated torque here, we divided by KD and KM here.
我们在这里乘以KD和KM。所以，总体收益现在是1，然后我们将其添加到
We multiply by KD and KM here. So, the overall gain is now one and then we add that to the
实际的干扰和由于这里的负号，干扰被抵消了。
actual disturbance and because of the negative sign here, the disturbance is cancelled out.
这是前馈控制的本质。这是一个非常巧妙的技巧。
This is the essence of feed forward control. It is a really neat trick.
我们可以采用的另一种策略是增加此刻的积分增益等于
Another strategy that we can adopt is to increase the integral gain at the moment is equal to
零。所以，我要把比例增益放回一个，我会增加
zero. So, I’m going to put the proportional gain back to one and I’m going to increase
积分增益值为1。我们将模拟它，看看会发生什么。
the integral gain to a value of one. We are going to simulate that and see what happens.
我们看到的是，方波响应的过度射击已经减少。它的
What we see is that the over shoot on the square wave response has been reduced. It's
当我们将比例增益等于1时，回到之前的状态。
back to what it was previously when we had the proportional gain equal to one.
在这里，我们可以看到积分项的影响发挥作用。当外部干扰
And here we can see the effect of the integral term coming into play. When the external disturbance
在时间5应用，控制系统中的错误增加。然后将其整合
is applied at time five, the error in the control system increases. That is then integrated
随着时间的推移产生一个随时间增加的扭矩，从而推动误差
over time to produce a torque which increases over time so as to push the error towards
零。我们可以在这里看到整合术语的影响。它正在推动这个错误
zero. We can see here the effect of the integrated term ramping up. It’s pushing the error
下。从我们可以看到的是经过一段时间后，整合的向上
down. From what we can see is an after short amount of time, the upward of the integrated
已经变得等于外部干扰的价值。它已经有效取消了
has become equal to the value of the external disturbance. And it has effectively cancelled
出来。因此，我们可以看到追踪的末尾
it out. So, we can see towards the end of the trace
方波响应几乎是我们想要的。外部干扰
that the square wave response is pretty much what we want it to be. The external disturbance
被拒绝了。让我们总结一下。我们研究了许多不同的技术
has been rejected. Let’s summarize. We've looked at a number of different techniques
减少干扰对机器人关节位置的影响。我们开始了
to reduce the effect of disturbance on the position of a robot joint. We started off
看一个非常标准的比例导数，通常称为PD控制器
looking at a very standard proportional derivative typically known as a PD controller which got
像这样的控制律，比例增益乘以位置误差加上导数
a control law like this, a proportional gain multiplied by the position error plus a derivative
增益乘以速度，有助于在关节移动时控制射击。
gain multiplied by the velocity which helps to control over shoot when the joint is moving.
我们看到误差量与增益P成反比。现在，我们可以增加
We saw that the amount of error is inversely proportional to the gain P. Now, we can increase
P减少错误，但是有一些不利后果如增加
P to reduce the error, but that has a number of adverse consequences such as increasing
过度拍摄或向电机提供无法实现的信号。
over shoot or providing signals to the motor that it cannot possibly achieve.
然后我们看了一个增加一个完整的术语。直觉是，随着不断的错误，
We then looked at an adding an integral term. The intuition is that, with the constant error,
积分随着时间的推移是一个斜坡上升的信号，增加了扭矩以便相反
the integral over time is a signal that ramps up which increases the torque so as to oppose
首先引起干扰的扭矩。
the torque that’s causing the disturbance in the first place.
我们研究的第三种方法是前馈控制，它试图预测或估计
The third approach, we looked at, is feed forward control which attempts to predict or estimate
干扰然后取消它。前馈控制的一大优势是
the disturbance and then cancel it out. A great advantage of feed forward control is
即使你对干扰是什么有一个不完美的估计，也有一些取消
even if you have a not perfect estimate of what the disturbance is, some cancellation
肯定比没有取消更好。在实践中，我们经常使用混合物
is certainly better than no cancellation at all. In practice, we often use a mixture of
反馈和前馈控制。它们各有特殊的优势和优势。
feedback and feed forward control. They each have particular strengths and advantages.